Guide to the Frank Karl Papers WAG.192
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frank Karl Papers
1940-1990
1980-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Karl, Frank
WAG.192
4.25 Linear Feet in four record cartons and one folder.
Frank Karl was president of Albany, New York Local 1151 of the Communications Workers of America (CWA) from 1958 to 1990. He served on the union's national bargaining committee, and helped establish several key programs in labor-management relations, work safety, and counseling and support services. The collection is comprised for the most part of CWA records, including bargaining files, agreements, contracts, annual reports, committee updates, correspondence, and training material. Also included are some of Karl's academic papers, including his Master's thesis on the history of collective bargaining between the CWA and AT&T.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Frank Karl, 2002. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2002.005 and 2002.009.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Frank Karl was born in the small town of South Bethlehem, NY, just outside of Albany. Later the family moved to Albany, where he attended school. He graduated from Hudson Valley Community College with an Associates degree in 1956, and soon went to work for AT&T (and joined Communications Workers of America, Local 1151) in Albany. He became actively involved in union affairs in 1958, during heated debates over whether the Local should support a Western Electric strike that was on at the time. In the same year he was elected president of the Local, a position he was to hold for the next 33 years. Frank Karl retired from both AT&T and the CWA in 1990. As president, Karl administered an annual budget of $60,000 and was responsible for a membership, at its peak, of 340, a figure which represents well over 90% of eligible AT&T employees in the area.. Karl served on the CWA's national bargaining committee, which successfully negotiated six successive contracts on behalf of 87,000 AT&T Long Lines employees. In 1978, he was instrumental in establishing one of the first AT&T/CWA labor-management Common Interest Forums; he then served as the Forum's co-chair through 1990; he was also co-chair of the National AT&T/CWA Safety Advisory Council. In 1980, Karl helped to design and implement the first joint labor-management Employee Assistance Program (EAP) in the Bell System, a program that provided a range of counseling and support services to union members. After retiring in 1990, Frank Karl and Barbara, his wife of 50 years, realized a lifelong dream of building a house in the Adirondack Mountains. Karl, ill-suited to the sedentary life, got involved in local politics, and was soon elected Town Supervisor of Franklin, NY, a post he held for two consecutive terms. He later served on several local boards and committees to work on veterans' rights and environmental issues. Karl earned a Bachelor of Science degree in Industrial and Labor Relations, as well as a Masters degree in Labor and Policy Studies, both from Empire State College (SUNY). Frank and Barbara Karl raised five children.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is comprised for the most part of CWA records, including bargaining files, minutes, agreements, annual reports, committee updates, correspondence, photographs, and training material. Also of interest are papers and correspondence on the impact of AT&T divestiture on CWA employees, papers and reports on CWA and AT&T history and structure, and some of Frank Karl's academic papers, including his Master's thesis on the history of collective bargaining between the CWA and AT&T.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, General Files
Related Materials
Records of the Communications Workers of America, District 1 (WAG 117)
Records of the Communications Workers of America (WAG 124)
Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Labor unions -- Officials and employees.; Labor unions and international relations -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Telecommunication -- Employees -- Labor unions.; Telecommunication -- Law and legislation -- United States.; Telecommunication -- United States -- History.; Strikes and lockouts -- Telecommunication.; Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; Contracts; Agreements.; Arbitration, Industrial |z United States.; Collective labor agreements -- Telecommunication.; Corporate divestiture -- United States.; Collective bargaining -- United States.; Reports.; Albany (N.Y.); American Telephone and Telegraph Company--Employees; Communications Workers of America; American Institute for Free Labor Development; American Telephone and Telegraph Company; United States. National Labor Relations Board; American Telephone and Telegraph Company--Reorganization; Karl, Frank; Karl, Frank
- Series I: Subject Files
  - Academic Papers, 1973, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agreement I, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement II, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agreement, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agreement, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agreement, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agreement I, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agreement II, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Agreement: Supplement, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AT&T Job Briefs, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining I, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining II, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bargaining, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining I, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bargaining II, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bargaining, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bargaining I, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bargaining II, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bargaining III, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bargaining IV, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bargaining V, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bargaining VI, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bargaining: Agreements, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bargaining: Bargaining Information Network, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bargaining: Contract Articles I, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bargaining: Contract Articles II, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining: Contract Articles I, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining: Contract Articles II, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining: Contract Articles III, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bargaining: Contract Interpretation, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining: Contract Ratification, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining: Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bargaining: Demands, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bargaining: Local Presidents'Conference on Collective Bargaining, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bargaining: Minutes I, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bargaining: Minutes II, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bargaining: Pension Plan I, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bargaining: Pension Plan II, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bargaining: Personal Minutes I, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bargaining: Personal Minutes II, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bargaining: Personal Minutes III, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bargaining: Reports, 1963-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bargaining: Resolutions I, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bargaining: Resolutions II, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining: Wage Zones Consolidation, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Benefits and Wages, 1940-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - CWA History and Structure, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Contracts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Divestiture, 1982-1984, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Divestiture: Stiso Paper, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Economic Stabilization Act, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Employee Assistance Program (EAP) I, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Employee Assistance Program II, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Employee Assistance Program, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Annual Reports, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Brochures, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Correspondence, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Meetings, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Orientation, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Oversight Committee, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Employee Assistance Program: Oversight Committee, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Employee Counseling Program, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Heath Care Reform, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Labor Law Reform, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Labor-Management Relations, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Medina Upgrade, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mobilization, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - New York Times Insert on Communications Workers of America, Apr 7, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Panorama of Collective Bargaining: The CWA and ATT 1938-1989 (Master's Thesis), 1991 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Photographs depicting committees and conferences from the Communications Workers of America, 1959-1989 (Box A005)
  - Pittston Coal Strike, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Quality of Work Life (QWL), 1980s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Quality of Work Life: Common Interest Forum, 1982-1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Quality of Work Life: Handbook, Part I, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Quality of Work Life: Handbook, Part II, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Quality of Work Life: Northeast Network District Quality Council, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Quality of Work Life: Regional Vitality Task Force, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Quality of Work Life: Training Material, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Quality of Work Life: Workplace of the Future, 1987, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Safety Advisory Committee, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Safety Advisory Committee, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Safety Advisory Committee, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Safety Advisory Committee, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Safety Advisory Committee, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Safety Advisory Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Strike, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Strike: New York Telephone, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Technology, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 35)